Finding Aid for School of Kinesiology (University of Michigan) publications, 1945-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Kinesiology (University of Michigan) publications 1945-2013, 1981-2013
University of Michigan. School of Kinesiology.
44.8 MB online
0.6 linear feet
0324 Bimu 2
The School of Kinesiology was founded as the Department of Physical Education in the School Education in 1921. With expanded curriculum including movement science and sports management and communication it became a separate degree granting division in 1990. Publications include annual reports, course bulletins, and newsletters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 8840 ).
The publications group is open without restriction.
The interest in and instruction of physical education became more formalized in 1898 after the completion of the Waterman and Barbour Gymnasiums. Courses were designed and the Board of Regents resolved that course work in physical education would be a requirement for graduation from the university. The Department of Physical Education was created in 1921 and placed in the newly created School of Education. Physical education continued to grow as a discipline of study. The Department of Physical Education was separated from the School of Education in 1984, becoming the Division of Physical Education, a separate degree-granting academic unit. In 1990 it became the Division of Kinesiology to reflect the broadening of its curriculum to include movement science and sports management and communication. The Division was renamed the School of Kinesiology in 2008.
For additional background on this unit, please consult the history found in the University of Michigan. School of Kinesiology Records finding aid.
The Division of Kinesiology Publications are divided into two series: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications. The bulk of the publications document the period from 1981 to the present. Major publications include, annual reports, course bulletins, newsletters and the division website.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. School of Kinesiology.; University of Michigan. Division of Kinesiology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Education.; University of Michigan. Division of Physical Education.; University of Michigan. Adult Lifestyle Program.; University of Michigan. Center for Fitness and Sports Research.; University of Michigan. Fitness and Sports Research Laboratory.; University of Michigan. U-Move Office.; Kinesiology.; Physical education and training--Michigan.
Publications:
Kinesiology: a Michigan tradition, 1894-1994.; Division of physical education alumni newsletter.; Movement.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Education.; University of Michigan. Division of Physical Education.; University of Michigan. Adult Lifestyle Program.; University of Michigan. Center for Fitness and Sports Research.; University of Michigan. Fitness and Sports Research Laboratory.; University of Michigan. U-Move Office.
Genre Terms:
Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Catalogs, College.; Histories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the School of Kinesiology. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication. Previous to 1990 this unit was known as the Department of Physical Education and the Division of Physical Education.
  The Unit Publications include annual reports published from 1987 to 1989. There are also bulletins or course catalogs which describe courses offered by the Division of Physical Education and the Division of Kinesiology for the period from 1987 to 1998. The researcher should consult the School of Education Publications (0347, Bimu, C202, 2) for bulletins, from 1921 to 1984, with descriptions of courses offered by the Department of Physical Education. The electronic version of the School of Kinesiology bulletin, from 1998 to the present, is the authoritative source of admission information, course offerings and degree requirements for both undergraduate and graduate programs. Many of the bulletins contain addenda as well as student forms, the latter of which are record sheets used for tracking progress in program requirements and electives for the school's different programs.
  The history Kinesiology: A Michigan Tradition, 1894-1994 was written to celebrate the centennial of physical education instruction on the University of Michigan campus. This series also contains several manuals describing the study of physical education for both men and women as well as an information handbook for majors, minors and dance students. There are also three newsletters found in this series. The Division of Physical Education Alumni Newsletter covers the years 1985 through 1986. The alumni newsletter Movement was first published in 1988 and continues to the present. It describes the activities and research of the faculty, staff, students and alumni. The 1984 issues of Physical Education Newsletter are available here. The researcher should consult the School of Education Publications for 1983 issues.
  - Annual Reports
    - University of Michigan Division of Physical Education Annual Report, 1987-1989, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Graduate Studies, 1969-1971, undated (Box 1)
    - Kinesiology, circa 1995, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1992-2002, undated (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - 1985/86 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
    - 1992
      - Bulletin (Box 1)
      - Master's degree programs (Box 1)
    - 1995 (Box 1)
    - 1998
      - Bulletin (Box 1)
      - Course descriptions (Box 1)
    - 1998-2001, .ZIP files
      - Bulletin
      - Bulletin Addendum
      - Student Forms (record sheets)
    - 2001-2002, .ZIP files
      - Bulletin
      - Bulletin Addendum
      - Student Forms (record sheets)
    - 2002-2003, .ZIP files
      - Bulletin
      - Bulletin Addendum
      - Student Forms (record sheets)
    - 2003-2004, .ZIP files
      - Bulletin
      - Course Descriptions
      - Student Forms (records sheets)
    - 2004-2005, .ZIP files
      - Bulletin
      - Course Descriptions
      - Sports Management Course Descriptions Addendum
    - 2005-2006, .ZIP files
      - Bulletin
      - Course Descriptions
    - 2006-2007, .PDF files
    - 2007-2008, .PDF files
    - 2008-2009, .PDF files
    - 2009-2010, .PDF files
    - 2010-2011, .ZIP files
      - Bulletin
      - Bulletin Addendum
    - 2011-2012, .ZIP files
      - Undergraduate Bulletin
      - Graduate Bulletin
    - 2012-2013, .ZIP files
      - Undergraduate Bulletin
      - Graduate Bulletin
      - Bulletin Addendum
    - 2013-2014, .ZIP files
      - Undergraduate Bulletin
      - Graduate Bulletin
    - Elective Courses in PE undated (Box 1)
  - Flyers
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - E-mail printouts 2003 (Box 1)
  - Histories
    - Kinesiology: A Michigan Tradition, 1884-1994, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Faculty Information Manual, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Information Handbook for the Physical Education Major, the Physical Education Minor, the Dance Concentrate and the Dance Minor, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Physical Education for Men Information Handbook, 1957-1968 (Box 1)
    - Physical Education for Women Information Handbook, undated (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Division of Physical Education Alumni Newsletter, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - Movement, 1988-[ongoing], 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Physical Education Newsletter, 1977-1978, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - A Report Concerning Physical Education at the University of Michigan, 1945 (Box 1)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the School of Kinesiology. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit and include brochures from the Adult Lifestyle Program for the period from 1982 to 1995, undated brochures describing the Athletic Training Program, the Facility Management Program and Sports Facilities Research Laboratory, and U-Move brochures dating from 1996 to 2004, with some gaps. There is a single issue dated 1982, of the Center for Fitness and Sports Research Newsletter. There is also a 1981 newsletter entitled Exercise & Fitness from the Fitness and Sports Research Laboratory.
  - Adult Lifestyle Program
    - Brochures 1982-1995 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Training
    - Brochures undated (Box 1)
  - Center for Fitness and Sports Research
    - Brochures undated (Box 1)
    - Newsletters
      - The Center for Fitness and Sports Management, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Facility Management Program and Sports Facilities Research Laboratory (Box 1)
    - Brochures undated (Box 1)
  - Center for Human Motor Research
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Fitness and Sports Research Laboratory
    - Newsletters
      - Exercise and Fitness, 1981 (Box 1)
  - U-Move Office
    - Brochures
      - 1996-2000 (Box 1)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 1)
- Archived School of Kinesiology Website
  The Archived Website series documents the academic programs, accomplishments, resources, events, and people at the School of Kinesiology. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as newsletters and course catalogs), and information about admissions, curriculum, degree requirements, faculty, and the overall mission of the School. The website series is arranged chronologically, with captures from 2002 stored on CD. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Website capture May 15, 2002, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Website capture, May 22. 2002, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Archived School of Kinesiology home page 2010-[ongoing]
  - Archived websites related to the School of Kinesiology 2010-[ongoing]